The text and comment in today’s
Examining the Scriptures Daily
今日の聖句と注解は—
「待つ態度をどのように
保てますか」という—
was taken from a
Watchtower study article with the theme
ものみの塔の研究記事から
取られています
“How Can We Maintain ‘a Waiting Attitude’?”
なぜ今この点を考えるのか
記事にはこうあります
That’s a timely question
for all of us to ponder
because as that Watchtower said:
“辛抱できずにいら立つのは危険です”
“Impatience can be dangerous,
“性急に行動してしまう
可能性があるからです”
for it can cause us to behave rashly.”
What’s the antidote to impatience?
どうしたら ずっと
待っていられますか？
Open, please,
your Bible to the theme text
どうぞミカ 7章7節をお開きください
for that Watchtower study
at Micah 7:7,
これは研究記事の主題聖句です
and let’s read Micah 7:7 together
ミカ 7章7節を一緒に読み—
and consider for a few moments
how Micah’s good example
待つ態度を保つ上で ミカの良い手本が
助けになることについて—
can help us to maintain a waiting attitude.
少しの間考えましょう
That text reads:
こうあります
“But as for me,
I will keep on the lookout for Jehovah.
“しかしわたしは
終始エホバに目を向ける”
“わたしの救いの神を待ち望もう”
I will show a waiting attitude.”
改訂版の脚注の考えを含めると
“わたしの救いの神を辛抱強く待とう”
Or as the footnote says:
“I will wait patiently
“for the God of my salvation.
My God will hear me.”
“わたしの神は聞いてくださる”
It’s beautiful
that in just that one verse,
心に残る聖句です
three times Micah refers
to his God—our God—Jehovah.
このたった1節の中でミカは—
自分の そしてわたしたちの神
エホバについて3度述べています
And that’s a nice reminder
that no matter what the situation is
そして次のことが分かります
that may cause us to have feelings
of impatience or frustration,
もう望みはない 限界だ
そう感じる状況に置かれるとき—
whenever we put a problem
or difficulty side by side
問題をエホバにゆだねると
どうなりますか？
with our God, Jehovah,
what happens to the situation?
小さく見えるようになります
It appears smaller
—manageable with his help.
エホバの助けで
扱いやすいものになるのです
カール･クライン兄弟は
ライフ･ストーリーでこう語りました
We might conclude, as did Brother Karl Klein
as published in his life story,
“それが生じることを
神が許しておられるなら—”
that ‘if Jehovah permits it,
we can take it.’
“それに耐えることができる”
With Jehovah’s help, we can patiently endure
エホバの助けがあれば
どんな試練や状況のもとでも—
any trial, circumstance, or situation
喜びを失わず
踏みとどまることができるのです
as long as necessary without losing our joy.
ミカも そう確信していました
Micah was confident of that.
Look again at chapter 7 and verse 7.
もう一度7章7節をご覧ください
By saying that he would
“keep on the lookout for Jehovah,”
ミカは “終始エホバに
目を向ける”と述べています
in effect, Micah was saying
that he was determined
つまり 自分は物見の塔の上にいる
見張り番のようになる と言っていたのです
to become like
an active sentry on a watchtower.
情景を描いてみましょう
So let’s try to picture that:
見張り番がしっかりと目を開けて
辺りを注意深く見張っています
A wide-eyed watchman on high alert.
That was Micah, spiritually speaking.
ミカは霊的な意味でそう言いました
待ち切れなくなったり—
He was determined not to get impatient
自分ではどうにもならないこと
について考えていら立ったりはしない—
and not to get frustrated
with things that he could not change.
ミカはそう決意していました
Was it easy for Micah
to maintain a waiting attitude?
しかし 待つ態度を保つのは
簡単でしたか？
Probably not.
おそらくそうではなかったでしょう
Notice the context that reveals
what circumstances were like
文脈を見ると 当時のイスラエルと
ユダの状況が分かります
in Israel and in Judah
in Micah’s time.
Notice as you consider
some of the thoughts there
ミカ 7章2節以降で
幾つかの点に注目しましょう
beginning in verse 2
of Micah chapter 7.
“忠節な者は地からうせ”た
He says: “The loyal one
has perished from the earth.”
3節では “その手は悪事の上にある”
Verse 3: “Their hands
are expert at doing what is bad.”
4節には “彼らの最も善良な者は
おどろに似ており—”
Verse 4: “Their best one is like thorns,
“最も廉直な者もいばらの垣根に
勝らない”とあります
their most upright one
is worse than a thorn hedge.”
実際ミカは5節で
“仲間を信じてはいけない”
In fact, in verse 5, he says:
“腹心の友をも信頼してはいけない”
“Do not put faith in your companion
or trust a close friend.
“あなたの懐に寝る女に対して
口を開くことにも用心せよ”
Guard what you say to the one
who lies in your embrace.”
Verse 6: “For a son despises his father,
6節では “息子は父を軽んじ
娘はその母に逆らい—”
“a daughter rises up against her mother,
“嫁はそのしゅうとめに
逆らっているからである”
“and a daughter-in-law
is against her mother-in-law;
“人の敵はその家の者たち
となっている”と言っています
a man’s enemies
are the men of his household.”
Yes, times were difficult
when Micah was alive.
ミカは難しい時代に生きていました
邪悪なアハズ王の時代—
During wicked King Ahaz’ rule,
イスラエルは霊的にも道徳的にも
堕落し悲惨な状態でした
the spiritual and moral conditions in Israel
deteriorated to an appalling state.
Can you relate to Micah’s circumstances?
ミカの置かれていた状況は
あなたとも関係がありますか？
All of Jehovah’s people today
experience a test of endurance,
エホバの民は皆 忍耐や辛抱を試されます
a test of patience,
because we’re living in a selfish world
利己的な世で暮らしているからです
where, according to the Scriptures,
聖書によると 人々は
“感謝”しない “忠節”でない—
people are “unthankful, disloyal,”
they have “no natural affection.”
“自然の情愛”を持たない者になります
True Christians are
“objects of hatred,” as Jesus foretold.
イエスの予告通り 真のクリスチャンは
“憎しみの的”です
Some of our brothers
and sisters experience
学校や職場で ほぼ毎日 憎まれ
反対されている兄弟姉妹がいます
hatred and opposition
at school and at work
nearly every day.
時には家族の中で 真理にいない
家族から憎まれることもあります
Sometimes that hatred
is within the family,
from unbelieving family members.
Think, too, about the hatred
that our brothers and sisters
憎しみを受け 投獄されている
兄弟姉妹たちもいます
have experienced who are imprisoned.
アゼルバイジャンの2人の姉妹について
考えずにはいられません
I can’t help but think
about the two sisters in Azerbaijan,
不当な迫害を受けている姉妹たちのため
わたしたちは熱烈に祈っています
who we’re praying fervently for
because of their unjust persecution,
また エリトリア ナゴルノ･カラバフ
シンガポール 韓国 トルクメニスタンの—
or 600 more in Eritrea,
Nagorno-Karabakh, Singapore,
South Korea, and Turkmenistan.
600人以上の兄弟たちのことも考えます
わたしたちは 不公正が
正されることを待ち望んでいます
Those are injustices
that we long to see corrected.
状況が変化するよう心から願っています
We’d love to see
those situations changed today!
では 辛抱できずいら立つでしょうか？
But are we impatient?
No.
We cultivate a waiting attitude.
いいえ 待ち続けます
Added to these circumstances
are the health problems
加えて 多くの兄弟姉妹は
健康の問題に直面しています
that many of our brothers
and sisters are facing.
これも 辛抱や忍耐を試みられる状況です
These too are tests of patience,
tests of endurance.
あなた自身 あるいは
家族や友人のだれかが—
Maybe you’re dealing with a health challenge
or a family member or a friend of yours
程度は様々でも こうした問題と
闘っているかもしれません
is battling one of these
to a greater or lesser degree.
今月のBroadcastingで パナマの
サビナ･エルナンデス姉妹が登場しました
It made me think of the broadcast
for this month, for December,
where we met
Sabina Hernandez, in Panama,
姉妹には 生まれながらに
重い障害があります
who was born with a severe handicap.
Since birth, her life
has been anything but normal.
生まれた時から
普通の生活ができていません
But what an encouragement she is!
でも 姉妹の手本は本当に励みになります！
She’s come to trust in Jehovah.
エホバを信頼し
待つ態度を身に着けてきました
Like Micah,
she’s developed a waiting attitude,
and this sister is doing her best
健康の問題があっても
ベストを尽くしてエホバに奉仕しています
to serve Jehovah
despite her health challenge.
すべての問題がなくなる時を
心待ちにしています
She looks forward to the day
when those circumstances will change,
and we do too.
本当にその時が来てほしいですね
We’d love to see it today, wouldn’t we?
Of course, those problems will end,
間もなく すべての問題がなくなります
and likely it will happen
sooner than we think.
思ったより早くその時が来るでしょう
But whether the end of our circumstances
しかし それがもうすぐだとしても
もう少し後だとしても—
that are so difficult
comes today or a little later,
ミカの手本から何か学べるでしょうか？
what can Micah’s example teach us?
Well, think a little deeper about Micah.
もう少し考えましょう
Micah served faithfully
ミカは およそ60年忠実に奉仕し—
for some six decades,
some sixty years.
エホバの裁きに関するメッセージが
その通りに実現するのを目にしました
He did live to see the fulfillment of some
of Jehovah’s judgement messages.
預言者としての活動の成果を見たのです
He did see some good fruitage
from his prophesying activity.
ではミカは 約束すべてが
実現するのを見ましたか？
But did Micah live to see the fulfillment
of all of Jehovah’s promises?
いいえ
No.
では 辛抱して待ち 活動し続け—
So, what helped him to wait patiently,
to keep active,
to be confident in Jehovah?
エホバを信頼していられた
のはなぜですか？
It was his absolute confidence
いずれエホバが約束通り必ず行動される
と確信していたからです
that Jehovah would in time
fulfill all of His promises.
エホバを信頼し切っていたのです
He trusted completely in Him.
Well, by way of a reminder,
what two practical steps
では ミカと同じような信頼 確信をもって
待つ態度を培うため 何ができますか？
could we do or do more fully
that will help us to cultivate
さらにできることがあるでしょうか？
that same trusting,
confident waiting attitude?
2つ 思い起こしてみましょう
1つが テサロニケ第一 5章17節にあります
The first is the text found
at 1 Thessalonians 5:17;
読んでみましょう
テサロニケ第一 5章17節です
let’s read that together,
1 Thessalonians 5:17.
暗記しているかもしれません
Perhaps you have it memorized.
英語では簡単な2つの言葉です
It’s one of the easiest verses to do that
—two words.
何ができますか？
What does it tell us to do?
“絶えず祈りなさい”
“Pray constantly.”
祈りはエホバとのコミュニケーションです
We need to remember that prayer
is real communication with God.
話し過ぎと注意されることは
決してありません
We can never be charged
with talking too much to Jehovah.
ものみの塔はこの聖句を引用し
こう述べています
When it comes
to real communication with God,
“ご意志を行なう人がささげる祈りに
制限を設けてはおらず—”
The Watchtower cited this text and said:
“He is willing to listen endlessly
to those who do his will.”
“快く聴いてくださるのです”
Let’s accept that invitation.
では エホバの勧めに応じましょう
Let’s pray constantly
about the things that distress us.
苦しんでいることについて絶えず祈り—
Let’s cultivate the trust
in him by praying specifically
助けが必要なことについて
具体的に祈り 信頼を保ちましょう
about the things that we need help with.
では いつも祈りながら
踏みとどまってきましたが—
But what if we pray constantly
and we’re enduring a situation
and the problem persists?
問題がまだなくならない場合は
どうですか？
What then?
ルカ 11章9節のイエスの言葉は
本当に確信を強めてくれます
Notice Luke 11:9, please.
Jesus’ words give us
every reason for confidence
“それゆえにわたしはあなた方に言います”
when it says at Luke 11:9:
“求めつづけなさい
そうすれば与えられます”
“So I say to you, keep on asking,
and it will be given you;
“探しつづけなさい
そうすれば見いだせます”
“keep on seeking,
and you will find;
“たたきつづけなさい
そうすれば開かれます”
keep on knocking,
and it will be opened to you.”
Yes, we want to do
whatever is in our power
問題を解決するため できることをします
そして いずれエホバが解決してくださる—
to solve our problems,
having confidence that in time Jehovah
will give us the solution
その時まで立っていられるよう
助けてくださる と信じ続けるのです
and until then he’ll help us endure.
Remember what happens to a mountain
when it’s put next to Jehovah.
山のような問題は
エホバのそばに来るとどうなりますか？
It becomes a molehill.
小さなもぐら塚です
We need to turn mountains into molehills
では祈って 心配をエホバに渡して
山を小さな塚にしましょう
by throwing our concerns
upon Jehovah in prayer.
ミカの確信は報われます
Micah’s confidence was not misplaced.
復活し 辛抱して待ってきた
エホバの約束が実現するのを見るのです
Soon he’ll be back with us
in the resurrection
to witness the fulfillment of all
of Jehovah’s promises
では ミカのように
信仰を保って見張り続け—
that he patiently waited for.
So, like him, may we curb
our natural feelings of impatience
待ち切れなくなる
自然な気持ちを乗り越え—
いつも“エホバに目を向け”て
いることができますように
by keeping wide awake in faith,
always “on the lookout for Jehovah.”